what is up fellow game developers my
name is tyler parts and welcome back
to the tyler podge channel where today
we are going to be creating a
tap to or tut click to move game in 2d
so first thing we'll do is open up unity
hub using uh unity 2019.3.9 f1
and we're going to select 2d and i'm
just going to call this
uh click to move
click create and that is going to open
up unity for us so i will see you once
it has
loaded
okay so unity has now opened and we are
left with the sample scene now this is
perfect
all we need to do is in the bottom right
right click
create a sprite and i'm going to create
a so i create a hexagon i was supposed
to create a circle but we're now going
with hexagon because it's what i
accidentally created
you can use any sprite it doesn't have
to be a
hexagon and let's just drop this into
our scene
let's just drop him at zero zero
and there we go so now it has been
dropped in
we are now going to basically
just i'm going to rename it to player
because it will be our player we're
moving
or you could have units you're moving or
anything you want to move
for now we're going to click add
component i'm going to call this
um well rigid body 2d
gravity scale 0 and collision to
continuous again we don't actually need
this for this tutorial but it's sank
you'll probably be adding anyway
let's add a component and call it player
movement
hit enter create a new script and click
create and add now this
creates a new script once unity compiles
this script
we'll be able to open it up in visual
studio code so if i double click this
here we are we now have official studio
code open i'll zoom in a little
um and what we're going to do is we're
going to remove everything in here
we're going to put this back and this
script is fairly simple we give
our player a speed which i'm going to
set to 10 f this is how fast we move
towards the mouse or the position we
clicked we then need a vector 2
called last clicked or
last clicked position
we then need a boolean called moving um
which obviously will define whether we
are moving or not moving
lastly we need to open up the update
method we need to create an
if input
dot get mouse button down and we're
going to pass through 0 which
is our left mouse button we're then
going to say last clicked position is
equal to
camera dot main dot world or screen
to world point and we're going to pass
through
input if i can
input dot mouse
position if i can spell and there we go
simple as that we don't want to say
moving is equal to true
we're then going to say if moving
and then we're going to say and
transform
dot position we need to cast this as a
vector 2
because as we'll get an error saying you
can't confirm it it's not equal to
last clicked position so basically we're
just saying
if we if we're moving and our
and we're not um at the same position as
where we clicked
um we're then going to move so we're
going to say
uh step float called step which will be
our um speed times by time dot
delta time which means we'll only move
uh
it basically means we if our computer is
running at 10 frames per second
we will only be moving our speed by 10
frames or not by 10 volts
we'll basically be creating a delta time
obviously which means per
frame it gets a time between the frames
and it multiplies it by that which means
we're not if we if we have a slower
computer we won't be moving faster
because we have a slower computer we'll
be moving at the same speed
um and then we can now say transform
dot position is equal to a
a vector2 dot
move towards and we're going to say
transform
dot or transform transform
that's our first parameter so we're
saying where we are we're going to say
last clicked position is to where we're
aiming to go and then we're going to
pass through our step
um which is perfect and then we need to
do an else on this and say
moving is equal to false
so what we're saying here is if we are
moving and we're not equal to our last
clicked position
we're going to move towards the last
click position else
we're just going to we're not going to
be moving anymore so that means we've
either made it to our last click
position
or we're no longer moving which is fine
so if we go back to unity now
and we click play you'll now see
we move to wherever we click
which is perfect so now we'll forever be
moving
to where we're clicking
as you can see we can click anywhere we
can even click
midway to change its direction
and if you wanted to you could actually
set up an array of these
um so if you click here and then click
there it won't automatically change your
way until it gets to point one
then move to point two you can go click
click click and it will move to each one
first before it then
um stops which is you do an array and
you loop through the first index or
array once you've got to the first
index of the array you remove it you
then check again you
go for the second one blah blah all the
way down until you get to your position
but we're not going to be doing that in
that video this is all we're doing in
this video because it is a simple
click to move tutorial if you would like
to see
touch controls on this which is very
straightforward um i'll happily
do a mobile touch control so you can see
how it works
um on a phone so you can touch to move
your character around
for now guys i hope you enjoyed this
video if you did leave a thumbs up
smash that subscribe button and ring
that bell and i will see you
in the next video thank you for watching
guys and peace
[Music]
now