hello friends welcome to code basics
coding tutorial in this tutorial we are
going to see what is git
when you ask this question to anyone the
usual answer you get is
git is a version control system
but hey
what is version control system
let's look at the problems that we
encounter when you don't use version
control system so let's say you have a
computer and you are writing code on
that computer so the code files are
saved locally on that computer's hard
disk
but what if your hard disk crashes or
your computer has
some kind of problem
in that case whatever code you have
written is lost
second problem is if multiple people
want to contribute to
that code then they cannot do it if it
is on one computer even if it is let's
say these two people have
their own computers and if they want to
work on the same code how do they do
that
they have to transfer files using a pen
drive from one computer to another and
they have to do code merge manually
which is quite cumbersome
third problem you have is there is no
tracking of versions so let's say you
have your code it is working fine and
you are
making one more enhancements or you are
fixing some bugs so you made some
changes and let's say it doesn't look
good so you want to go to previous good
version of your code
but
there is no way if you have your code on
your computer because the simple file
system doesn't give you
a version tracking
so you have all these different issues
especially when you're working on a
bigger code base or a sample project you
will encounter these issues again and
again
version control system solves all these
problems
let's look at all these problems one by
one and see how
vcs or version control system solves
these issues
so our first problem was hard disk
failure
inversion control system
the code is saved on cloud cloud is
basically some remote machine which is
much more stable than your local
computer
and it is guaranteed that you will never
lose your code from cloud
so you store your code on the cloud and
then you sync the files to your local
computer
that way if you have hardware problem or
some computer breakdown you can always
get your code back from the cloud
so problem number one fixed
problem number two
multiple people contributing to the same
code base
again
you have your golden copy of your code
on the cloud so that
these two people can work on their
individual
computers
and then whenever they're ready
uh to push their changes they will push
it to a cloud
now let's say if they're working on a
same function let's say here there is a
function
python function def sum and if they're
they both are making uh changes to the
same function then there are merge tools
available which can help you resolve the
conflict so merging is pretty easy these
two people can work on their own
without worrying about anything
so it's it's very beautiful
how uh vcs solves these issues or of
collaboration
problem number theo three was uh version
tracking
in version control system uh you have
all of your
changes tracked down through different
versions of the same file so let's say
you have this file called foo dot py
which has some
uh a function called sum
and let's say right now the function
looks like this it just returns a plus b
but if you make some changes later on
and if you save it it will be saved as
version number two i was number three
and so on so at any given point of time
you feel like i i want to go back to the
previous old version which was working
okay you can do it very easily
now there are different
version control systems available in the
market
for example git
mercurial subversion etc
but git is by far the best version
control system
i will tell you two reasons
number one is it is a distributed
version control system
where
the version history is maintained on
your local computer
as well as it is maintained on the cloud
so let's say you are
in some area where you don't have
internet internet connection
you still have an ability to try
to track the versions
uh and whenever you have intercon
internet connection you can sync it up
with your uh remote which is your
copy in the cloud
the second biggest benefit of using it
is
github
the most popular website to host code is
powered by get
that was all about
git
thank you for watching