welcome to core basics coding tutorial
and this episode we are going to see
what is github and why is it so popular
github is a website that allows you to
store your code onto the cloud now don't
think of github as just a cloud storage
it is a full-fledged version control
system power bi get so without
discussing it any further let's look at
the demo so first we'll go to this
website github calm here if you want to
upload your code or if you want to
contribute to someone else code you need
to create your login so creating login
is pretty straightforward you give it
your email ID and password and you can
sign up for github I am already signed
up that's why I will just use sign-in
button and log into my account ok so I
had this account and I have this
repository called py where I store all
of my Python code so you see like I have
all these Python files and my readme
file which is here and bunch of
directories and here what I have is all
my commit history so whatever code I
have committed all the versions and
everything is stored so if you want one
if I want to go back to any of the
previous commit I can easily go and
check what happened during that coming
ok now I have the same codebase
synced up on to my local computer here
in this directory so this is py charm
Python code editor and as you can see
here I have same list of files and
directories for example I have debugging
modules multiprocessing
so it's basically all these files I have
them stored on this github cloud storage
cloud storage is basically something
like Gmail so Gmail you can access it
from anywhere because it is not stored
locally on your device computer or it
could be a cell phone it is stored
somewhere else so you can access it
anytime similarly github is a cloud
where my code is stored so if I want to
log in from some other computer and make
my code changes I can always do it okay
now it is powered by a good version
control system if you already don't know
what is version control system I would
suggest that you go and watch my video
on the version control system okay so
now I will show you how to make code
change and push it to our github
repository repository is basically this
particular area it's like a directory
with all the files and subdirectory into
it so that's what I call a repository or
a repo repo is a short form so learn P
is my login name and py is my repository
okay so I have this particular code
which is not functioning the way it
should so I am making some code changes
here okay and I made my code changes
higher on the program I make sure it
works fine yes it is working fine so now
I am ready to push my changes to get now
before I make this changes let me show
you what - dot py has on github so on
github as you see I added these two
lines ok but in github it is still my
old code ok so I just got that code I
added these two lines to fix some issue
and now I am going to push my changes to
github so I will say right-click git
commit directory whatever changes I have
I just want to commit it so I will save
fixed a bug in taste dot py and I will
say gump commit and push so what this
will do is this will push my changes to
upstream to here ok
and now if I look at my commit log here
you see fix a bug in test or py whatever
I committed 11 seconds ago it is visible
here and if I click here on this commit
ID it will show me the difference you
see these two lines are highlighted I it
says that I added these two lines ok so
now my code is pushed and if I look at
this dot py file I have those two lines
added here so this is a quick demo of
how you push your changes to your github
okay let me now cover some of the
interesting features of github the most
important feature of github is a pull
request
what pull request does is it allows you
to collaborate with other projects in
this diagram there is this github repo
let's say this is some inventory
management system right so this is the
code for inventory management system it
has bench of files and restore on github
repo that's why I have shown it in the
cloud and these people are kind of the
owner of tag repo these are the people
who write or who wrote that code ok now
let's see this person acts he wants to
make Jeanne in into this code for that
he will just simply fork the code fork
means just simply copying the code to
his own private space so again this is
in the cloud which is which means it is
on github but it is a private repository
which means it is this person's private
space and he will sync up the code to
his local computer he will make changes
for example in this function this blue
line is the chain that this guy made and
he will push it to his own cloud after
that once he is done making his changes
and he tested his code and he's good to
go
he will sand or request to these people
asking to pull his changes into the main
repository so he will say ok hey guys
I'm done with my change can you please
pull my change
into your repository and these people
using our code review they will
basically pull the question as a code
review so they will do a code review and
if it if it looks good to them then they
will accept the pull request so that's
how the code will get merged here now
pull requests is becoming a central
theme in open source world so an open
source project anyone can contribute to
the open source code so most of the open
source projects are nowadays on github
and the people who contribute to these
projects using a poll request are that's
why a github github is becoming very
popular because it has such a good
support for collaboration and open
source projects okay there are some
other useful features of github status
issues issue tracking you know if you
have a code base it will allow you to
track issues or Viki which means it will
allow you to write documentation on your
code pulse which will give you different
pulse and graph both will give you a
different statistics and I will quickly
show all these four features to you so I
have this sample code repository which I
found it through Google and on this repo
has this issue list so if you click here
so here you see your main code and then
here you see all the issues so people
will report all these issues here you
can go to issue you can have a
screenshot attached you can give a
description reproduction condition and
so on and then there there is a pull
request feature which I just talked
about by showing that diagram then there
is a wiki so wiki is short of like a
documentation so for my code base
for this html5 boilerplate code base the
owner of this repository has put all
this nice documentation so you can click
through
wait you can read through all the
documentation you can go to different
website etcetera ah there is a pulse and
graph feature which just shows you the
pulse on your project so basically
ongoing activity on your project so here
on this project I have some 0 mod
politicus 1 open pull request and so on
and one issue so it is sort of like your
dashboard and then there are graphs
which will show you different statistic
graph like contributors so these are the
people who are contributing activity to
this cool repo there are comments so on
this day there were nine commits so
there was highest amount of activity on
this particular day ah there is core
frequency Network member and so on so it
has all this nice useful feature but the
most important thing about github is
this whole website itself it's a nice
GUI graphical user interface that allows
you to see your core and of various
dimensions of various statistics on your
code ok so these were basically the four
other features that that were that there
are important features for using github
now there are some interesting facts
about github it is very popular nowadays
or there are 14 million users with 35
million code repositories some of the
popular open source projects such as
Linux kernel has been posted on github
so if you go to this link github.com
tour was less Linux you will see the
code for Linux there I would say let's
try this so let's go to github.com
tour was Linux and I'm having some
internet issue but it's eye graphics ok
so this is the code base for Linux so
you can actually see the Linux kernel
core base here and if you feel like you
want to contribute to this project then
you can click on this button and form
the repository and basically follow this
diagram to make code changes and when
you send back the pull request the owner
of that repository will give you your
code changes and it will possibly be
merged if things look ok so see it's so
powerful there is a Linux kernel and you
can now contribute to Linux kernel just
because of github ok so that is all
about github thank